A Guide to the Papers of Susan Dabney Smedes, 1818(1886-1907)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Susan Dabney Smedes Correspondence 2655,-a
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2655,-a
This collection consists of twenty letters.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the Library by Richard H. Dabney of the University of Virginia, on April 15, 1947.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 1818(1886-1907) contains twenty letters pertaining to Memorials of a Southern Planter by Susan Dabney Smedes (1840-1913). The book is a memorial to her father, Thomas Dabney, and discusses his life and the lives of Southerners in general. The letters deal chiefly with impressions of the book and how sales are going in Great Britain. There is also a letter, July 14, 1890, from Jeanie D. Hogg to a Mrs. Mussell, concerning the latter's travels in America, Dr. Henry Anderson's estate, Mrs. Dahgleish, and news from Edingburgh, Scotland.
In addition, there is a letter, May 8, 1899, from A. D. Brydon to Richard Heath Dabney (1860-1947), University of Virginia, on behalf of "a worthy but poor family," offering to barter some books with the Randolph Coat-of-Arms as well as two autographs of John Randolph for articles of clothing. Enclosed with this plea for assistance are: an 1818 letter of John Randolph to "Mr. Carrington," concerning Randolph's feelings of respect toward Carrington's father, [Paul Carrington (1733-1818)], who recently passed away, and a falling out with him in the past; and, a franked letter cover addressed to Beverley Tucker.
There are letters, 1907 March-April, of Andrew Lang and newspaper clippings pertaining to an incident between Lang and Smedes. Lang poked fun at Smedes' book, Memorials of a Southern Planter, and the author's name in verse. Smedes' nephew, Richard Heath Dabney, a University of Virginia professor, rebutted with a verse of his own, causing Lang to apologize profusely. Apparently, Smedes was amused by the affair.
Contents List
- Letters pertaining to Memorials of a Southern Planter
  - Augustus [John Cuthbert] Hare (1834-1903) 1886 July 9
  - Lord Northington 1887 Nov 8
  - Augustus [John Cuthbert] Hare 1887 Nov 13
  - Sir Henry Frederick Ponsonby (for Queen Victoria) (1825-1895) 1887 Dec 14
  - C[harlotte]; M[ary] Yonge (1823-1901) 1888 Feb 10
  - William E. Gladstone (with printed reproduction and the prefatory notice) 1889 Oct 12
  - John Murray (publisher) (1808-1892) 1889 Nov 4
  - J. A. Froude 1889 Dec 29
  - Charles Dudley Warner (author) (1829-1909) 1890 Jan 17
  - J. A. Froude 1890 Mar 21
  - Jeanie D. Hogg (daughter of the Ettrick Shepherd) to Mrs. Mussell 1890 July 14
  - John Murray 1890 Aug 14
  - John Murray, account 1891 Dec 31
  - John Murray 1892 Dec 13
  - John Murray 1896 Feb 14
  - Andrew Lang (1844-1912) 1907 March 2
  - Andrew Lang 1907 March 3
  - John Murray 1907 April 16
  - unidentified ANS n.d.
  - Newspaper clippings concerning Andrew Lang and Susan Dabney Smedes 1907
- Letter of Richard Dabney Heath
  #2655-a
  - A. D. Brydon to R. H. Dabney, with [1818] letter from John Randolph of Roanoke to Mr. Carrington, and a franked letter cover from John Randolph of Roanoke to Beverley Tucker 1899 May 8